family. Uh we are getting ready to get
into the word of God this morning. And
if you're ready and if you're excited,
please put up one in the chat because uh
I will let you know right now the
message that is going to be preached
today uh is highly significant and
highly relevant especially to end time
events. And so today's message is
entitled the day of the Lord. And um
we're going to see exactly what this day
of the Lord is and not only what it is,
but why it is. And so with that said,
we're going to have a word of prayer.
I'm going to get right into the message.
Let's do that now. Heavenly Father,
bless us Lord as we open your word. I
pray Lord in a very special way that you
would give your people understanding.
Lord, please speak through your servant
today. Is my prayer in Jesus name. Amen.
Amen.
Beloved, the first thing that I want to
share with you as we go to the screen
for the message entitled the day of the
Lord is that there are three distinct
days of the Lord in the Bible. Three
distinct day of the Lords in the Bible.
Notice with me Isaiah 13:6.
The Bible says, "How ye, for the day of
the Lord is at hand. It shall come as a
destruction from the Almighty. Now, this
is the prophet Isaiah speaking. And the
question is, what is Isaiah referring to
as he's speaking to his own people,
Israel, and warning them of this day of
the Lord to come, this destruction from
the Almighty?
And the answer is is in its context.
Isaiah is referring to the destruction
of Jerusalem by Babylon.
He is using
prophetic language to describe this
destruction that that uh Jerusalem will
experience because of their rejection of
the Lord. And so what you'll find is
that in the Old Testament, uh there are
prophets that are what we call
pre-exilic meaning these prophets
wrote before the destruction of
Jerusalem by Babylon. And they were all
warning of the same event. They were
warning Israel to repent, to return from
their wicked ways. uh uh otherwise this
day of the Lord would come upon them.
And that day of the Lord was the
destruction of Jerusalem by Babylon. And
so you'll notice with me the book of
Lamentations,
chapter 2, 21 and 22. The Bible says
here, "The young and the old lie on the
ground in the streets. My virgins and my
young men are fallen by the sword. Thou
hast slain them in the day of thine
anger. Thou has killed and not pied.
Thou hast called as in the solemn day my
terrors round about so that in the day
of the Lord's anger none escaped nor
remained. Those that I have swallowed
and brought up hath mine enemy consumed.
Again we find here this is in reference
to the same day of the Lord. We find it
again in Ezekiel 7 19.
They shall cast their silver in the
streets and their gold shall be removed.
Their silver and their gold shall not be
able to deliver them in the day of the
wrath of the Lord.
They shall not satisfy their souls,
neither fill their bowels because it is
the stumbling block of their iniquity.
Ezekiel was warning of the same thing.
We find it again in Ezekiel 13:5. It
says here, "You have not gone up into
the gaps, neither made up the hedge for
the house of Israel to stand in the
battle in the day of the Lord." We find
it again in Zephaniah 1 7 and 8. Hold
thy peace at the presence of the Lord
God, for the day of the Lord is at hand.
For the Lord has prepared a sacrifice.
He has bid his guests. And it shall come
to pass in the day of the Lord's
sacrifice that I will punish the princes
and the king's children and all such are
clothed with strange apparel. We'll look
at one more verse in this context.
Zephaniah 1 verse 14 and 15. The great
day of the Lord is near. It is near and
hasteth greatly. Even the voice of the
day of the Lord. The mighty man shall
cry there bitterly.
That day is a day of wrath, a day of
trouble and distress, a day of wastess
and desolation, a day of darkness and
glooiness, a day of clouds and thick
darkness. And so what I want you to
understand here is that we everything we
have laid out so far was in reference to
the first day of the Lord.
This is
referring to the children of Israel or
Jerusalem being destroyed by Babylon.
Now, we're we're laying the foundation
here for something absolutely
mind-blowing. So, so put a one in the
chat if you're following so far. The
simple point we have made thus far is
that the prophets who wrote before the
destruction of Jerusalem by Babylon
referred to that destruction as the day
of the Lord. Now I said there were three
days of the Lord in the Bible. We're
going to now go to the second day of the
Lord.
Now, this second day of the Lord, you're
going to find prominent in the prophets
who came after the destruction of
Jerusalem by Babylon. In other words,
after Jerusalem was set free from
Babylon and they went back to Jerusalem,
the Jews went back to Jerusalem, rebuilt
their city and their temple.
Now, you had a new set of prophets
rising, warning of another day of the
Lord. So notice with notice with me Joel
chapter 1 verse1 15 alas for the day
alas for the day for the day of the Lord
is at hand and as a destruction from the
Almighty shall it come. What day of the
Lord is Joel talking about here? Joel
chapter 2 verse one and two. Blow ye the
trumpet in Zion and sound an alarm in my
holy mountain. Let all the inhabitants
inhabitants of the land tremble, for the
day of the Lord cometh, for it is nigh
at hand. A day of darkness and
glooiness, a day of clouds and of thick
darkness, as the morning spread upon the
mountains. Joel here is referring to
another day of the Lord. And this one
has to be future of the one that
happened when Babylon destroyed
Jerusalem. This is another day of the
Lord that the children of Israel are
being warned about. Again,
we find this in Joel 2:31.
The sun shall be turned into darkness
and the moon into blood before the great
and terrible day of the Lord. We find it
in Joel 3:14. Multitudes, multitudes in
the valley of decision, for the day of
the Lord is near in the valley of
decision. And then we find it in Malachi
4:es 1 and 5. This is the last book of
the Old Testament. And here's what it
says. For behold, the day cometh that
shall burn as an oven, and all the
proud, yay, all that do wickedly shall
be stubble,
as the day that cometh shall burn them
up, say the Lord of hosts, that it shall
leave them neither root nor branch. And
notice verse five. Behold, I will send
you Elijah the prophet before the coming
of the great and dreadful day of the
Lord. These prophets who lived after the
destruction of Jerusalem by Babylon
are warning of a second day of the Lord
to come. We find this as well in
Zechariah chapter 14 verse1. For behold,
the day of the Lord cometh and the spoil
shall be divided in the midst of thee.
So the question now is this.
What is this second day of the Lord that
these postexilic prophets are pointing
to? How what are they warning the Jews?
What kind of danger or destruction are
they warning the Jews about? What are
they saying is coming? Well, if you
remember
on the day of Pentecost when the Holy
Spirit is poured out upon Peter and the
disciples, you'll remember that Peter
stood up to to preach. And you'll
remember he says something very, very
interesting. In Acts chapter 2:14,
listen to what the Bible says here. But
Peter standing up with with the 11
lifted up his voice and said unto them,
"Ye men of Judah and all ye that dwell
at Jerusalem, Be known unto you, and
hearken to my words, for these are not
drunken as you suppose, seeing that it
is but the third hour of the day." Now
watch this.
But this is that which was spoken by the
prophet Joel. So, this is the same
prophet we just read. The same prophet
that was talking about or warning about
this coming day of the Lord. Listen to
what it says here. This is that which
was spoken by the prophet Joel. And it
shall come to pass in the last days,
sayaith God. I will pour out my spirit
upon all flesh, and your sons and your
daughters shall prophesy, and your young
men shall see visions, and your old men
shall dream dreams. Here Peter
is using Joel to refer to the time that
he is in that Peter is speaking as the
last days. Now I know what you're
thinking. The last days? How could that
be the last days when
the world is still around today? What
last days was Peter saying was upon
Israel? Let's keep reading.
Acts chapter 2:1 18. And on my servants,
so he's still quoting Joel. And on my
servants and on my handmmaids, I will
pour out in those days of my spirit, and
they shall prophesy. And I will show
wonders in heaven above, and signs in
the earth beneath, blood, and fire and
vapor of smoke. The sun shall be turned
into darkness, and the moon into blood
before the great and notable day of the
Lord come. And it shall come to pass
that whosoever shall call on the name of
the Lord shall be saved. And so
to make this plain,
the second day of the Lord that these
postexelic prophets were speaking about
was none other than the destruction of
Jerusalem by Rome.
This would have been the second day of
the Lord. The prophets are using endtime
language to point to the coming
destruction of Jerusalem. In fact, let's
go back to the book of Joel chapter 2
verse one and note what Peter is quoting
in Joel 2 vers1. It says, "Blow you the
trumpet in Zion and sound an alarm in my
holy mountain. Let all the inhabitants
of the land tremble, for the day of the
Lord cometh, for it is nigh at hand, a
day of darkness and of glooiness, a day
of clouds and of thick darkness, as the
morning spreads upon the mountains."
Watch this now.
A great people and a strong. There has
not ever been the like. Neither shall be
any more after it, even to the years of
many generations. A fire devourth before
them, and behind them a flame burneth.
The land is as the garden of Eden before
them, and behind them a desolate
wilderness. Yay, nothing shall escape
them. Joel here
is equating the day of the Lord with
this coming army that would destroy
Jerusalem.
Who was that army? It was the Roman
army. This is the same verse that Peter
quotes on the day of Pentecost saying,
listen, repent and accept the Messiah
because if you do not, an army is
coming.
He's quoting Joel. an army is coming
that's going to destroy the this temple
and city because of your rejection of
the Messiah.
And so, beloved, this is the second day
of the Lord in the Bible. I said there
were three days of the Lord. Here is the
third day of the Lord. Let's go to the
book of First Thessalonians
5 2 and 3. The Bible says, "For
yourselves know perfectly that the day
of the Lord so cometh as a thief in the
night. For when they shall say peace and
safety, then sudden destruction cometh
upon them as travail upon a woman uh
with child, and they shall not escape."
First Thessalonians is speaking
literally about the second coming of
Jesus Christ, which is in fact the third
day of the Lord. Y'all put a one in the
chat if you're following. If this makes
sense so far, there are three days of
the Lord, the third being the actual
destruction of the world. Again in first
Thessalon 2 Thessalonians I'm sorry
chapter 2 verse two the Bible says that
you be not soon shaken in mind or be
troubled neither by spirit nor by word
nor by letter as from us as that the day
of Christ is at hand. The day of the
Lord is the day of Christ. It is the
time of the second coming in second
Peter chapter 3 10 through13. But the
day of the Lord will come as a thief in
the night, in the which the heaven shall
pass away with a great noise, and the
elements shall melt with fervent heat,
and the earth also, and the works that
are therein shall be burned up.
Nevertheless, we according to his
promise look for new heavens, and a new
earth, wherein dwelleth righteousness.
And so
to recap,
the first day of the Lord, which the
pre-exilic prophets were all referring
to,
were not events to take place at the end
of time. Rather, they were events that
marked the end of the days of Jerusalem
by the Babylonian Empire.
After Jerusalem is destroyed, it is
years later rebuilt. Israel has a second
chance, but they begin to rebel against
God again. And new prophets rise up
warning of a second day of the Lord.
That second day of the Lord was
fulfilled in the Roman destruction of
Jerusalem in 70 AD.
But the Bible tells us there is a third
and final day of the Lord in the which
the heavens and the earth will will be
destroyed. That is a global event. This
is the second coming of Jesus Christ.
Now with that in mind, with that in
mind, what we want to ask now is a very
simple question.
Why did the first day of the Lord come
in the first place? That's the question.
That's the basis of this message today.
Why did the day of the Lord come in the
first place? Now, to answer that
question, it might seem like, oh, why
are we going here? But I need to take
you back to the book of Genesis. Back to
the book of Genesis.
And uh we're going to go we're going to
go in fact, you know what? Before we go
to the book of Genesis, let me just read
just just several more verses to you.
Revelation 6 and 17, notice what it says
here. uh the wicked at the end of time
cry out to the mountains and rocks,
saying, "Fall on us, and hide us from
the face of him that siteth on the
throne, and from the wrath of the lamb,
for the great day of his wrath is come,
and who shall be able to stand." So, so
the question here is why the wrath of
the lamb, why the wrath of the lamb? Let
me share with you the book of Hebrews
chapter 3:es 7-9.
So in Hebrews chapter 3:es 7-9, God is
Paul is speaking a and he's using the
analogy of the children of Israel in the
Old Testament as they were journeying to
the promised land. And I want you to
notice what he says here.
Wherefore, as the Holy Ghost saith,
Today, if you will hear his voice,
harden not your hearts, as in the
provocation, in the day of temptation in
the wilderness, when your fathers
tempted me, and proved me, and saw my
works 40 years. Wherefore I was grieved
with that generation, and said, They do
always heir in their heart, and they
have not always known my ways. So I
swear in my wrath they shall not enter
into my rest. Now guys, pause for a
second.
There are two options here. There is the
wrath of God and there is the rest of
God.
Those who who who do not enter into the
rest of God experience the wrath of God.
So when we just read that verse where
the wicked are crying out, "Hide us from
the wrath of the lamb." It is because
they did not enter into the rest of the
lamb. If y'all with me so far, put a two
in the chat, pastor. We get it. The
wrath of God, the day of the Lord,
which equates with the wrath of God, is
reserved for those who entered not into
rest.
Okay? So, so with that in mind, now we
want to answer the question, well, why
was the first day of the Lord, the wrath
of the Lord? Why did that come about?
Why did Jerusalem get destroyed by the
Babylonian Empire? Why did God allow
that? And to answer that question, we
first need to go back to the book of
Genesis. We're going to go to Genesis
chapter 2. And I want you to note here
with me, Genesis chapter 2, verse one.
The Bible says here, "Thus the heavens
and the earth were finished, and all the
host of them. And on the seventh day,
God ended his work which he had made.
And he rested on the seventh day from
all his work which he had made. And God
blessed the seventh day and sanctified
it because at it he had rested from all
his work which God created and made."
This is the first time in the Bible we
see God resting. And it is in connection
with the seventh day. God has entered
into rest. And this rest is because he
created the world in six days. And he
saw that everything was good. And so the
Sabbath was a sign that man was was was
submitted to the will of God. That man
and the earth everything was good.
Everything was good. So the Sabbath was
God's sign of of God's work of God's
finished and completed work.
Now we know that man sinned.
And when man sinned, uh, death and sin
and corruption came upon the earth. And
as we read through the book of Genesis,
even into the book of Exodus, we see
that the children of that that uh, uh,
the children of Israel end up in
Egyptian captivity. And and then God is
going to deliver them out of captivity.
And then in Exodus 20, he gives them the
Sabbath uh, uh, as a nation. So he first
gave it in Genesis, but now he's
repeating this commandment. He's he's
he's letting the children of Israel who
had been in captivity for 400 years,
he's reminding them of the Sabbath. And
the text says in Exodus 20:8, "Remember
the Sabbath day to keep it holy. Six
days shalt thou labor and do all thy
work, but the seventh day is a Sabbath
of the Lord thy God. In it thou shalt
not do any work. Thou nor thy son, nor
thy daughter, nor thy manservant, nor
thy maidervant, nor thy cattle, nor thy
stranger that is within thy gates. For
in six days the Lord made heaven and
earth the sea and all that in them is
and rested the seventh day. Wherefore
the Lord blessed the Sabbath day and
hallowed it. And so we see here God
reinstituting the Sabbath for his
people. Even in ex in Deuteronomy 5:12
and 13, we're told, "Keep the Sabbath
day to sanctify it as the Lord thy God
has commanded thee. Sixth day shalt thou
labor and do all thy work, but the
seventh day is a Sabbath of the Lord thy
God." It goes on to say in verse 15,
"And remember that thou was a servant in
the land of Egypt, and that the Lord thy
God brought thee out thence through a
mighty hand by a stretched out arm.
Therefore the Lord thy God commanded
thee to keep the Sabbath day." So here
we find that God has commanded the
children of Israel, "Keep my Sabbath
for two reasons. Number one, it is a
reminder of what I did at the beginning
of creation. And number two, it is a
reminder that I delivered you out of
bondage.
In the book of Leviticus,
Moses now lays out
some blessings and some curses for the
children of Israel. If they obey,
they're going to be blessed. But if they
don't obey, they're going to be cursed.
And I want you to notice what Leviticus
chapter 26:1 says. It says, "You shall
make no idols nor grave in image,
neither rear up a standing image,
neither shall ye set up any image of
stone in your land to bow down unto it,
for I am the Lord your God." Verse two,
you shall keep my Sabbaths and reverence
my sanctuary. I am the Lord. Now watch
this. If you walk in my statutes and
keep my commandments and do them, then
will I give you rain in due season, and
the land shall yield her increase, and
the trees of the field shall yield their
fruit. And then he goes on to list all
these blessings, right? And now he's
going to come to the curses. And I want
you to notice
what Moses says in the curses if you
don't obey. In verse 33, it says, "I
will scatter you among the heathen and
will draw out a sword after you, and
your land shall be desolate and your
cities waste." Watch this. Then shall
the land enjoy her Sabbaths. As long as
it lith desolate, and you be in your
enemy's land, even then shall the land
rest and enjoy her Sabbath. Let me ask
you guys a question. According to
Leviticus 26, Moses is prophesying of
what would happen to the children of
Israel if this if they disobey God. And
the key reason that God gives for the
children of Israel going into captivity
and their land being desolate would be
because they did not let they did not
observe the Sabbath in their land. Is
everybody on the same page so far?
In fact, note with me, notice with me 2
Chronicles 36 20 and 21. It says, "And
them that had escaped from the sword
carried he away to Babylon, where they
were servants to him and his sons until
the reign of the kingdom of Persia to
fulfill the word of the Lord by the
mouth of Jeremiah
until the land had enjoyed her Sabbaths.
For as long as she lay desolate, she
kept Sabbath to fulfill three score and
10 years." Do y'all see this? The first
day of the Lord, where Babylon destroyed
Jerusalem, was specifically
because the children of Israel refused
to honor the Sabbath. I'm not making
this up. Let's go to Jeremiah 17 27. But
if you will not hearken unto me to
hallow the Sabbath day, and to and not
to bear a burden, and enter in at the
gates of Jerusalem on the Sabbath day,
then will I kindle a fire in the gates
thereof, and it shall devour the palaces
of Jerusalem, and it shall not be
quenched.
That's pretty straightforward, you guys.
The reason Jerusalem was set on fire by
Babylon was specifically because they
had rejected the Sabbath.
In fact, Jeremiah 66:1 19
here, O earth, behold, I will bring evil
upon this people, even the fruit of
their thoughts, because they have not
hearkened unto my words, nor to my law,
but rejected it. In fact, in fact, as if
it couldn't be any more plain, I want
we're going somewhere with this.
So, please listen carefully.
In the book of Ezekiel chapter 20,
beginning with verse 12, the Bible says,
in fact, you know what? Let's start with
verse 6.
Ezekiel says, "In that day that I lift
up my hand," Ezekiel wrote this rather,
I should say, "In the day that I lift up
my hand unto them to lifted up my hand
unto them to bring them forth of the
land of Egypt, into a land that I had
aspired for them, flowing with milk and
honey, which is the glory of all lands."
Then said I unto them, "Cast ye away
every man the abomination of his eyes,
and defile not yourself with the idols
of Egypt. I am the Lord your God." But
they rebelled against me and would not
hearken unto me. They did not every man
cast away the abomination of their eyes.
Neither did they forsake the idols of
Egypt. Then I said, I will pour out my
fury unto them to accomplish my anger
against them in the midst of the land of
Egypt. Let's keep reading. But I brought
for my name's sake that it should not be
polluted before the heathen among whom
they were in whose sight I made myself
known unto them in bringing them forth
out of the land of Egypt. Wherefore I
caused them to go forth out of the land
of Egypt, and brought them into the
wilderness, and I gave them my statutes,
and showed them my judgments, which if a
man do, he he shall live in them.
Moreover, also I gave them my Sabbaths
to be a sign between me and them, that
they might know that I am the Lord that
sanctified them. Watch this. But the
house of Israel rebelled against me in
the wilderness. They walked not in my
statutes, and they despised my
judgments, which if a man do, he shall
live in them, and my Sabbaths they
greatly polluted. Then I said, I would
pour my fury upon them in the wilderness
to consume them. But I wrought for my
name's sake, that it should not be
polluted.
Yet also I lifted up my hand in the
wilderness that I would not that I would
not bring them into the land which I had
given them flowing with milk and honey
which is the glory of all lands. It goes
on beloved because they despise my
judgments and walked not in my statutes
but polluted my Sabbaths for their heart
went after their idols. Neither mine I
spared them from destroying them neither
did I make an end of them in the
wilderness. Verse 20. But I said unto
the children of children in the
wilderness, walk not in the statutes of
your father, neither observe their
judgments, nor defile yourselves with
their idols. I am the Lord your God.
Walk in my statutes and keep my
judgments and do them. And hallow my
Sabbath, and they shall be a sign
between me and you. Notwithstanding, the
children of Israel rebelled against me.
They walked not in my statutes, neither
kept my judgments to do them. Which if a
man do, he shall live in them. They
polluted my Sabbaths.
You guys,
how many times does he say it?
The reason the children of Israel went
into captivity is because they rejected,
they polluted the Sabbath of the Lord.
This is the reason for the first day of
the Lord. In Isaiah 58 verse 1 and two,
the Bible literally says, "Cry aloud,
spare not, lift up thy voice like a
trumpet, and show my people their
transgression and the house of Jacob
their sins." And he's going on telling
them about their sins. And then he
begins to tell them that the Sabbath
which God had given them was not to be
observed in any it was not to be
forgotten and was not just a day for
them to do whatever they wanted to. But
it says it was a day listen to this. Is
not this the fast I have chosen to loose
the bands of wickedness to undo the
heavy burdens and to let the oppressed
go free and that you break every yoke?
Is it not to deal thy bread to the
hungry? And that thou bring the poor
that are cast out into thy house? When
thou seest the naked, that thou cover
him? And when and you hide not yourself
from your own flesh. And if you draw out
your soul to the hungry, and satisfy the
afflicted soul, then shall thy light
rise in obscurity, and thy darkness
shall be as the noon day. If you turn
away your foot from the Sabbath from
doing your pleasure on my holy day, the
entire chapter of Isaiah 58 is rebuking
the children of Israel for not correctly
observing the command that God had given
them. And as a result, listen to me now
everybody,
the day of the Lord came upon Israel
because they refused to observe the day
of the Lord. Let me pause.
Let me pause.
The day of the Lord
came upon Jerusalem
because they refused the day of the
Lord.
In other words, the day of the Lord, a
day of wrath, came upon Jerusalem
because they rejected the day of the
Lord, a day of rest. They rejected the
rest and therefore experienced the
wrath. You got two options, beloved, is
what I'm trying to tell you.
The Israel had two options. They could
either honor the day of the Lord, the
day of rest, or face the day of the
Lord, the day of wrath. And so now that
we see that the first day of the Lord
came about as a result of the children
of Israel's rejection of the day of the
Lord, the Sabbath.
That sets the stage for our second
question.
Our second question is going to be,
well, what reason, pray, tell, did the
second day of the Lord happen?
I'm glad you asked. Let's find out.
When we go to the book of Nehemiah,
we find that Nehemiah who lives after
the destruction of Jerusalem by Babylon.
He is part of the rebuilding of
Jerusalem. And Nehemiah is trying to
make sure that the children of Israel do
not make the same mistake they made
before,
ignoring the day of the Lord. That's
what they did. They ignored it.
Nehemiah 13:1 17- 18 says this. Then I
contended with the nobles of Judah and
said unto them, "What evil thing is this
that you do and profane the Sabbath
day?"
I'm going to my verse 18 isn't up here,
so let me just read it in your hearing.
Did not our fathers thus? And did not
our God bring all this evil upon us and
upon this city? Yet you bring more wrath
upon Israel by profaining the Sabbath
rest. Note how the wrath of God Nehemiah
was warning. Listen, you remember why we
went into Babylon in the first place.
You remember why we experienced the
wrath of God? It's because we rejected
the rest of God. Are you about to do
this again? And so Nehemiah is rebuking
his own people. And the Sabbath uh
selling eventually stops. And so from
Nehemiah, we're now moving forward.
Remember, Nehemiah is post destruction
of Babylon. So the prophets that come
along with Nehemiah and afterward begin
to warn of this second day of the Lord.
Now why? What is Jerusalem doing or what
have they done? They're obviously not
obeying the word of God again. Which is
why these prophets are coming on the
scene warning of this day of the Lord.
Now let's fast forward to just some
years before 70 AD. We're going to go 40
40some years before 70 AD to when Jesus
the Messiah comes.
In in excuse me in Daniel chapter 9 in
verse 26 there is a prophecy given of
the time of Jesus's coming. Daniel 9:26
it says this. And after three scorn and
two weeks shall Messiah be cut off but
not for himself. And the people of the
prince that shall come shall destroy the
city and the sanctuary. This is that
second day of the Lord, y'all.
And the end thereof shall be with a
flood, and unto the end of the war,
desolations are determined.
What is it
that brought the wrath of God upon
Jerusalem the second time?
Let's find out.
We're going to go to Mark chapter 3:1.
In Mark 3:1, the Bible says, "And he
entered again into the synagogue, and
there was a man there which had a
withered hand, and they watched him
whether he would heal him on the Sabbath
day, that they might accuse him." Now,
let me pause for a second here.
As a result of the children of Israel's
first day of the Lord, Babylon, right?
the destruction of Jerusalem by Babylon
because they rejected the Sabbath,
because they forgot the Sabbath.
After the destruction of Babylon, and
after their rebuilding of their city and
temple,
they began to go the exact opposite.
They began to put rules
upon the Sabbath that you can't find in
the Bible. They began to become so
stringent and so strict on the Sabbath
that it is almost as though they
produced another Sabbath that wasn't in
the Bible.
They had rules on the Sabbath and and
and the way they treated the sab this
Sabbath was so was so uh rigid that it
was as it though as it were a totally
different Sabbath.
to the point that by the time Jesus
comes on the scene, they're watching
Jesus to see if he will heal on the
Sabbath to accuse him of breaking the
Sabbath.
You can't find thou shalt not heal on
the Sabbath anywhere in the Bible. You
can't find it. But they made that rule
up. So, let's keep reading.
It says, "And he saith unto the man
which had the withered hand, stand
forth." And he saved unto them, "Is it
lawful to do good on the Sabbath days or
to do evil, to save life or to kill?"
But they held their peace. And when they
had when he had looked around about upon
them with anger, being grieved for the
hardness of their hearts, he saith unto
the man, "Stretch forth thine hand." And
he stretched it out. And his hand was
restored whole as the other. And the
Pharisees went forth, and straightway
took counsel with the Herodians against
him, how they might destroy him. Now,
here's what I need y'all to notice.
This is Mark chapter 3.
This is very early in the ministry of
Jesus.
In fact,
it was this event
that planted the seed for the Pharisees
to kill Jesus.
This is the first time in the Bible that
the leaders say Jesus must die. And
beloved, that is significant because
they put Jesus, the Lord of the Sabbath,
to death in the name of the Sabbath.
Think about that for a moment, y'all.
The reason they put Jesus to death was
because they claimed that Jesus had
broken the Sabbath.
Let that sink in.
The seed,
the event
that led to their rejection of the
Messiah
was that he had broken their
misunderstanding
of the Sabbath.
Go with me to John chapter 5 verse 1-3.
After this there was a feast of the Jews
and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. Now
there is at Jerusalem by the sheep's
market a pool which is called in the
Hebrew tongue Bethesda which h having
five porches. In these lay a great
multitude of impotent folk and blind and
halt withered waiting for the moving of
the waters. And and for an angel went
down at a certain season in the pool and
troubled the water. Whosoever then
first, who whosoever then first after
the troubling of the water stepped in,
was made whole of whatever disease he
had. And a certain man was there which
had an infirmity 30 and 8 years. When
Jesus saw him lie, so he couldn't walk,
he knew that he had been long time in
this case. He saith unto him, "Wil thou
be made whole?" The impotent man
answered him, "Sir, I have no man when
the water is troubled to put me into the
pool, but when I'm coming, another
stepeth down before me." Jesus saith
unto him, "Rise up, take up rise, take
up your bed, and walk." And immediately
the man was made whole, and took up his
bed, and walked. And on the same day was
the Sabbath. The Jews therefore said
unto him that was cured, "It is the
Sabbath day. It is not lawful for thee
to carry thy bed." Again, no rule in the
Bible, none. He answered them, and said,
He that made me whole, the same said
unto me, Take up thy bed and walk. Then
asked they him, What man is that is that
which said unto thee, Take up thy bed
and walk? And he and he that was healed
wis not who it was. For Jesus had
conveyed himself away a multitude being
in that place.
Afterward Jesus findeth him in the
temple and saith unto him, "Behold, thou
art made whole. Sin no more, lest the
worst thing come upon thee." The man
departed and told the Jews, it was Jesus
which made him whole. Watch this. And
therefore did the Jews persecute Jesus
and sought to slay him because he had
done these things on the Sabbath day.
Beloved, please understand this.
The thing that set the Jewish nation in
motion to kill Jesus
was the Sabbath.
It was the Sabbath. This is absolutely
mind-blowing, beloved.
Because as we look at that other
example,
at that other example, notice with me
the book of Luke, I'm sorry, not the
book of Luke, the book of John, chapter
9, verse 1 and 2. And as Jesus passed
by, he saw a man which was blind from
his birth. And his disciples asked him,
saying, "Master, who did this sin, the
man or his parents that he was born
blind?"
Jesus answered, "Neither has this man
sinned, nor his parents, but that the
works of God should be made manifest in
him. I must work the works of him that
sent me while it is day. The night
cometh when no man can work. As long as
I'm in the world, I am the light of the
world." And when he had thus spoken, he
spat on the ground, and made clay of the
spittle, and anointed the eyes of the
blind man with clay, and said unto him,
"Go wash in the pool of Sylum, which is
by interpretation sent." He went his
way, therefore, and washed, and came
seeing. The neighbors therefore, and
they which before him had seen that he
was blind, said, "Is not he this he that
sat and begged?" Some said, "This is
he." Others said, "He is like him." But
he said, "I am he." Therefore said they
unto him, "How were thine eyes opened?"
He answered and said, "A man that is
called Jesus, made clay, and anointed
mine eyes, and said unto me, Go to the
pool of Silum, and wash, and I went and
washed, and I received my sight. Watch
this." Then said they unto him, "Where
is he?" He said, "I know not." They
brought to the Pharisees him that a four
time was blind. And it was the Sabbath
day when Jesus made the clay and opened
his eyes. Then again the Pharisees also
asked him how how he had received his
sight. He said unto them, he put clay
upon my eyes and washed and I do see.
Therefore the Pharisees said of some of
the Pharisees said, "This man of is not
of God because he keepeth not the
Sabbath day." All right, y'all.
They killed the Lord of the Sabbath,
the creator of the Sabbath over a
counterfeit version of the Sabbath.
And as a result,
think about this now.
On that Friday evening that they kill
Jesus,
they walk away to keep the Sabbath.
When in fact in killing Jesus, the Lord
of the Sabbath, they had broken the
Sabbath in the most egregious way.
They wanted to put Jesus to death to
spare their nation because Jesus was a
Sabbath breaker. And yet in putting
Jesus to death over the Sabbath, they
had in essence broken the Sabbath which
in essence brought about the second day
of the Lord upon them.
Jerusalem was destroyed by Rome because
Jerusalem rejected Jesus. Put him to
death and then thought they were keeping
the Sabbath.
Put the Lord of the Sabbath to death.
And in so doing,
they had broken the very essence and
spirit of the Sabbath. You see, let me
break something down to you.
Jesus healed
a crippled man
on the Sabbath,
a man with a withered hand on the
Sabbath,
and a blind man on the Sabbath.
And and I want you to note, beloved, all
those healings represented something. In
Ecclesiastes 9:10, the Bible says,
"Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do
it with thy might, for there is no work,
nor device, nor wisdom, nor knowledge in
the grave, whether thou goest." It's as
though the healing of the hand was to
was to in essence show that Christ came
to do a greater healing. Came to help us
to see what the work of God is, how to
do the work of God. He healed a crippled
man. The Bible says in Psalms 119:105,
"Thy word is a lamp unto my feet and a
light unto my path." It's as though in
healing the crippled man, God Jesus was
showing that he has come to make us able
to walk in the path of righteousness. He
healed a blind man. The Bible says,
"Open thou mine eyes." Psalm 119:18,
"Open thy mine eyes that I may behold
wondrous things out of thy law." It's as
though Jesus was trying to open the eyes
of the blind so that they could see the
light of the world.
In fact, beloved,
the very purpose of the Sabbath was to
loose the bonds of wickedness, to let
the captives go free. And the fact that
they killed Jesus
over his correct observation of the
Sabbath shows that they in essence had
rejected the Sabbath in a different way
than they had done back under the first
day of the Lord. They had rejected the
Sabbath by putting rules and regulations
and being strict about rules and
regulations God never applied to the
Sabbath. So much so that they killed the
Lord of the Sabbath. They had instituted
a counterfeit Sabbath and enforced it
with death.
Y'all put a five in the chat if you're
following so far because beloved, all of
this
sets up our third and final question,
which is
if the first day of the Lord came as a
result of the children of Israel
forgetting the Sabbath and the second
day of the Lord came as a result of the
children of Israel
implementing a counterfeit Sabbath so
strenuously and enforced that they put
the Lord of the Sabbath to death over
that counterfeit Sabbath.
The final question is
what brings about the third day of the
Lord?
That's a fair question, isn't it?
That would seem like a logical question.
What is it that brings about the third
and final day of the Lord? And beloved,
may I suggest to you that if the first
day of the Lord came as a result of
forgetting the Sabbath and the second
day of the Lord came as a result of a
counterfeit version of the Sabbath, then
could it be possible that the third day
of the Lord comes about as a combination
of the two? Could it be that the third
day of the Lord comes about as a result
of one forgetting God's true Sabbath and
two implementing a counterfeit one
with the force
of death behind it in the name of Jesus
in the name of God.
Come with me to Revelation 14:12 where
the Bible speaks about an end time
people who have the patience of the
saints. Here they the Bible says that
keep the commandments of God and the
faith of Jesus. We know that at the end
of time according to Revelation chapter
14:12 that there will be a
commandmentkeeping people of God. We
know that the text says that
might that have something to do with end
time events. The Bible says in
Revelation 12:1 17, the dragon was wroth
and went to was wroth with the woman and
went to make war with the remnant of her
seed which keep the commandments of God
and have the testimony of Jesus Christ.
Could it be possible, beloved, that at
the end of time that Satan will be out
to try to destroy the people who are
actually keeping the commandments of
God, not forgetting it like ancient
Israel and not altering it and coming up
with new rules and regulations that God
never commanded as happened in the in
the time of Jesus. Could it be possible
that the dragon is out to destroy those
people to remove that witness of a
people who actually do what God says to
do, who actually remember what God says
to remember? In fact, in Revelation 14 6
and 7, the Bible says, "I saw another
angel fly in the midst of heaven, having
the everlasting gospel to preach unto
them that dwell on the earth, and to
every nation, kindred, tongue, and
people, saying with a loud voice, fear
God, and give glory to him, for the hour
of his judgment is come, and worship him
that made heaven and earth and the sea
and the fountains of waters." Beloved,
please be aware that this is an end time
message that goes to the entire world.
And the last portion of that sentence is
lifted directly out of the fourth
commandment, which tells us that God is
the one who created the heaven, the
earth, and the sea, and all that in them
is. In other words, beloved, that angel
that is flying in the midst of heaven
with the everlasting gospel is coming
with a message, a warning
to avoid the same mistake that ancient
Israel made before the first day of the
Lord and before the second day of the
Lord, that there is coming a third day
of the Lord. And those who refuse the
rest of the Lord
will face the wrath of the Lord.
This is absolutely crucial to
understand. Beloved,
in Revelation 7:1, the Bible says,
"After these things, I saw four angels
standing on the four corner of the of
the earth, holding the four winds of the
earth, that the wind should not blow on
the earth, nor on the sea, nor on any
tree. And I saw another angel ascending
from the east, having the seal of the
living God, or the sign of the living
God." Remember, we read back in Ezekiel
that the Sabbath was the sign between
God and his people.
Beloved, you can't make this up.
That which brought about the first day
of the Lord and the second day of the
Lord will also bring about the third day
of the Lord. And it is interesting
beloved that that as the first day of
the Lord occurred in connection with
Babylon and the second day of the Lord
occurred in connection with Rome at the
end of time we have a power a power
called mystery Babylon that is symbolic
of Rome in a spiritual context.
Revelation 17:5 says upon and upon her
forehead was a name written mystery
Babylon the great the mother of harlots
and abominations of the earth. In the
Bible, a woman when used symbolically,
particularly in the book of Revelation,
is likened unto a church. So here,
beloved, in Revelation chapter 17, what
we have is a church being described as
Babylon,
but is also Roman in nature.
If we were to go back to the book of
Daniel 7:25, this same power is
described as a little horn. The Bible
says, "He shall speak great words
against the most high and shall wear out
or persecute the saints of the most high
and think to change
times and laws, and they shall be given
into his hand until a time, times, and
half a time." Beloved, there is one
power that came out of Rome and that the
Bible identifies as mystery Babylon.
This is a power, a church that has both
forgotten
God's Sabbath day and also implemented a
counterfeit version of it and said, "Do
this. Remember this." of whom the Bible
says the time is coming where they will
enforce this counterfeit by decree.
And just as Jesus was put to death
because he refused
to observe a counterfeit Sabbath.
That is the reason Jesus died.
He refused to observe a counterfeit
Sabbath. In the same way, this power
described in Daniel 7:25 will do the
same.
Here's a little bit of history for you.
Two simple quotes.
The first one is from Priest Brady
reported in the Elizabeth Elizabeth, New
Jersey news on March 18th, 1903. And
here's what he says. It is well to
remind the Presbyterians, Baptists,
Methodists, and all other Christians
that the Bible does not support them
anywhere in their observance of Sunday.
Sunday is an institution of the Roman
Catholic Church, and those who observe
the day observe a commandment of the
Catholic Church. How about this one? Our
Sunday visitor, February 5th, 1950.
Protestants accept Sunday rather than
Saturday as the day for public worship
after the Catholic Church, not Jesus,
after the Catholic Church made the
change. But the Protestant mind does not
seem to realize that in observing
Sunday, they are accepting the authority
of the spokesman for the church, the
pope.
Beloved, I want you to understand
that the Christian world today, not only
Catholic but Protestants as well, have
by and large not only embraced the error
that brought about the first day of the
Lord, forgetting God's true Sabbath, but
they've embraced the error that brought
about the second day of the Lord,
embracing a counterfeit Sabbath
that God never spoke
and the time is coming where that
counterfeit Sabbath will be enforced. In
fact, look in the Christian world today
and you will see talk of bringing of of
enforcing Sunday worship or legalizing
Sunday worship. You see it happening now
in this movement to bring the ten
commandments to schools all over America
because one of those commandments, the
fourth, has been forgotten
first day of the Lord and replaced with
a counterfeit second day of the Lord.
And God is looking for a people who at
the end of time will choose to obey God
rather than man.
Now come on. I got to show you one more
thing and then we're going to wrap this
message up. Remember back in Hebrews how
we read there, let us therefore fear
lest the promise being left us of
entering into his rest, any of you
should seem to come short of it. For
unto us was the gospel preached as well
as unto them. But the word preached did
not profit them not being mixed with
faith in them that heard it. For we
which believe do enter into that rest,
as he said, as I have sworn in my wrath,
if they shall enter into my rest,
although the works were finished from
the foundation of the world. Beloved, I
want you to understand that just as
those who on the first day of the Lord
experienced the wrath of the Lord
because they rejected the rest of the
Lord, that is the Sabbath, they were
they experienced the day of the Lord
because they rejected the day of the
Lord. So in the second day of the Lord,
they experienced the wrath of the Lord
because they rejected the rest of the
Lord. They experienced the day of the
Lord because they refused to rightly
honor the day of the Lord. So at the end
of time, beloved, those who experience
the wrath of the day of the Lord, it is
because they have rejected the the
Hebrews says there remainth therefore a
rest to the people of God.
That rest is in allowing Jesus to come
into you and give you rest from the
works of your flesh. Rest from
lawlessness, rest from Sabbath breaking,
rest from adultery, rest from murder,
rest from lying, rest from killing, rest
from covetousness, rest from having
other gods. That's what the rest is
about. And that rest
does not negate the commandments of God.
The devil was able to lead the to lead
those under the first day of the Lord to
say, "Ah, the Sabbath, we don't need to
keep it." He was able to lead those
under the second day of the Lord to say,
"Hey, we're going to set up a
counterfeit version of the Sabbath and
be really, really stringent with that
one."
Beloved, so he's seeking to deceive
people today
in two ways.
The Sabbath, oh, that's done away with.
That was for the Jews. And in the
meantime, we're just going to create a
new Sabbath. And maybe we'll call it the
Sabbath, and maybe we won't. But it'll
be something that we enforce
stringently.
Y'all know the rule. Y'all know the
tradition.
Let me show you before we close. You
have to see this in Nehemiah chapter 13.
The Bible says, "In those days I saw I
in Judah some treading wine presses on
the Sabbath and bringing in sheav and
latting asses as also wine, grapes, and
figs, all manner of burden which they
brought into R into Jerusalem on the
Sabbath day. And I testified against
them in the day which in wherein they
sold victuals.
There dwelt men of Ty also therein,
which brought fish, and all manner of
wear, and sold on the Sabbath unto the
children of Israel, and in Jerusalem.
Then I contended with the nobles of
Judah, and said unto them, What evil
things is this that you do, and profane
the Sabbath day? Did not your fathers
us? And did not our God bring all the
evil upon us upon this city? Yet you
bring more wrath upon Israel by
profaining the Sabbath. Watch this. And
it came to pass that when the gates of
Jerusalem began to be dark before the
Sabbath, I commanded that the gates
should be shut and charged that they
should not be opened till after the
Sabbath. And some of my servants set I
at the gates that there should no burden
be brought on the Sabbath day. So the
merchants and the settlers of all kind
of wear lodged without Jerusalem once or
twice. Then I testified against him and
said unto them, why lodge you about the
wall? If you do so again, I will lay
hands on you from that time forth came
they no more on the Sabbath. Why is this
significant?
Because beloved, the Bible tells us in
Revelation 21 27 that there shall in no
wise enter into the city anything that
defileth, nor whatsoever workketh
abomination or maketh a lie, but they
which are written in the Lamb's book of
life. Revelation 20 uh Revelation uh 18
tells us, "For all nations have drunk of
the wine of the wrath of her
fornication, and the kings of the earth
have committed fornication with her. And
the merchants of the earth," Pause for a
second, y'all, the merchants were the
ones who were outside of Jerusalem who
did not come in because they did not
honor the Sabbath. In the very same way,
beloved, at the end of time
in that new Jerusalem, the gates are
only open to those who obeyed the
commandments of God. The merchants
do not get to enter.
Those who are more concerned with making
a living than keeping. Those who are
more concerned with with with with
providing for themselves and doing their
own thing.
Those are the ones
that don't enter into the city.
Our closing text is this. Beloved,
Revelation 22:14 and 15 says, "Blessed
are they that do his commandments that
they may have right to the tree of life
and may enter in through the gates into
the city. For without are dogs and
sorcerers and whoreongers and murderers
and idoltors and whosoever loveth and
maketh a lie." Beloved, my appeal to you
today is very specific.
Do not make the mistake that was made
in the first day of the Lord. Do not
make the mistake that was made in the
second day of the Lord.
Keep the commandments of God.
Live by the testimony of Jesus.
Accept the rest of God. Accept the day
of the Lord. So that you do not have to
fear the day of the Lord. Accept the
rest of God. So you do not have to
experience the wrath of God. He has
shown it to us again and again in
scripture.
Let us not be blind.
Let us not be ignorant.
Let us not be willful
in disobedience to God.
Let us keep his commandments as he has
said, "If you love me, keep my
commandments."
And beloved, we will have right to the
tree of life. If it's your desire to
say, "Lord, yes, I want to keep your
commandments. I don't want to make the
mistake that was made under the first
day of the Lord, and I don't want to
make the same mistake that was made
under the second day of the Lord. I
wanna I want to experience your rest so
that I do not face your wrath.
I don't want to face the wrath of God,
but he invites me into the rest of God.
If that's your desire, put a one in the
chat as we pray. Heavenly Father, thank
you. Thank you for speaking to us today.
Lord, thank you for showing us this
pattern
of the way you worked to redeem and to
save your people. But how they continue
to reject either by going by forgetting
or becoming so uh uh
caught up in a wrong form of worship
that in both ways they ultimately
rejected the Sabbath and its true
meaning.
Please, Lord, help us to obey your
commandments, to not be led to the right
or to the left, but to obey your word as
you have written it. Write your law upon
our hearts and in our minds. And Lord,
seal us so that we may be ready for you
to come again. In Jesus name we pray.
Amen. And amen. May God bless you as you
continue to worship. May God bless you
as you continue to study and make the
word the supreme authority in your life.
And may this message uh reach and touch
your heart and put you and set you on a
path closer to Jesus is my prayer in
Jesus name. Again, amen. God bless you.
Thank you for joining us today. If this
is your first time worshiping with us,
please check out our website at
livingmana.urch. church. We are not just
here for Sabbath service. We have weekly
programming too that covers mental
health, physical health, weekly prayer
service, financial health, and proving
the existence of God. It is our desire
that our programming will continue to
bless you. Please continue to pray for
us as we fulfill God's mission to go
into all the world with the gospel of
Jesus Christ.
[Music]